Hello English learners, welcome back to another great lesson here at EnglishPod.
英语学习者你们好，欢迎回到EnglishPod的又一堂精彩课程。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
And I'm Erica.
我是Erica。
And today we are going to have a lesson that is going to be very useful when you arrive
今天这堂课在你迟到时会非常有用。
late.
迟到。
Yes, well, we all have arrived late to something and we need a good way of saying sorry and
是的，我们都有过迟到的时候，需要一种好的方式来说抱歉。
saying why we were late.
并解释迟到的原因。
So today we're not only going to be looking at vocabulary used to explain why you are
所以今天我们不仅要学习用来解释迟到原因的词汇。
late but also some typical excuses of why people are late.
还要了解一些典型的迟到借口。
Right, so some normal reasons for saying why you're late.
对，就是一些常见的迟到理由。
Well, why don't we get started with the dialogue.
那我们开始对话吧。
Now we're going to hear five people in the dialogue.
这次对话中我们会听到五个人。
So at the beginning we'll hear the boss and the assistant and then we'll hear three people
开头会听到老板和助理，然后会听到三个人。
who are arriving late.
他们是迟到的。
Where is everyone?
大家都去哪儿了？
Scotch has called and said that he's running late.
Scotch打电话来说她要迟到了。
His last meeting ran over, but he's on his way now.
她上一个会议超时了，但她现在正在路上。
Guys, this is not acceptable.
各位，这不可接受。
If I say the meeting starts at 10, the meeting starts at 10.
如果我说会议10点开始，那就是10点开始。
Not 10.01.
不是10点01分。
And definitely not 10.20.
更不是10点20分。
All right, let's get started.
好了，我们开始吧。
So the first thing I want to talk about is our-
首先我想谈谈我们的——
I'm really sorry everyone.
真的很抱歉，各位。
I know I'm late, but really it's not my fault.
我知道我迟到了，但这真的不是我的错。
I was getting a coffee at Starbucks and the line was way, way too long.
我在星巴克买咖啡，队伍排得太长了。
I was waiting for 20 minutes to get my coffee.
我等了20分钟才拿到咖啡。
All right, so well, good excuses in general, except the last one.
好吧，总的来说借口不错，除了最后一个。
I don't think that's such a good excuse of why you're late, right?
我觉得那可不是什么好借口，对吧？
Yeah, I don't really think if I was the boss, I would be very happy with this employee.
是啊，如果我是老板，我肯定不会对这个员工满意。
Yeah, I don't think coffee is that important.
对，我觉得咖啡没那么重要。
But some of the excuses were good and some of the language they used to describe the
但有些借口不错，他们用来描述借口的语言也很棒。
excuses was really great.
很棒。
So let's look at that now in Language Takeaway.
现在我们来看“语言要点”部分。
Language Takeaway.
语言要点。
All right, on Language Takeaway today we have four words that we're going to be looking
好的，今天的“语言要点”我们要看四个词。
at and well, let's get started with the first one.
我们先从第一个开始。
So Joe called the office assistant and explained that she will be late because she got tied
所以Joe打电话给办公室助理，解释说她因为被客户缠住了。
up with a client.
所以会迟到。
To get tied up.
被缠住。
So I got tied up with a client.
所以我被一个客户缠住了。
All right, this is a really common reason for being late, but why don't we listen to
好吧，这是迟到的常见原因，但我们不如听一些例子来理解它的意思。
some examples to help us understand what it means.
一些例子来帮助我们理解它的含义。
Example one.
例子一。
Sorry, I'm late, honey.
抱歉，我迟到了，亲爱的。
I got tied up at the office.
我在办公室被缠住了。
Example two.
例子二。
I was tied up on the phone all afternoon and didn't get any work done.
我整个下午都被电话缠住了，什么工作都没做成。
Example three.
例子三。
I got tied up in traffic on the way here.
我在来这里的路上被交通堵住了。
All right, so if you get tied up, it means that you get busy with something that you
好吧，所以如果你被缠住了，意思是你忙于一些无法避免的事情。
can't avoid.
无法避免的事情。
Right, you're busy with something that's so important, it's like you are tied by a rope
对，你忙于一些非常重要的事情，就像被绳子绑在那件事上一样。
to that thing.
被绑在那件事上。
Okay, I got tied up.
好的，我被缠住了。
I'm sorry, I got tied up.
抱歉，我被缠住了。
Yep.
是的。
All right, now the first person that arrived to the office will explain that there was
好吧，现在第一个到办公室的人会解释说高速公路上有严重的交通堵塞。
a huge traffic jam on the highway.
高速公路上有严重的交通堵塞。
A traffic jam.
交通堵塞。
A huge traffic jam.
严重的交通堵塞。
Now we understand traffic, right?
现在我们理解交通，对吧？
Cars, a lot of cars.
车，很多车。
Yep.
是的。
So a jam, it means that it was like blocked.
所以堵塞，意思是像被堵住了。
It was stopped.
被堵住了。
Yep.
是的。
There were a lot of cars on the highway and they weren't moving.
高速公路上有很多车，它们都不动。
So a huge traffic jam is a very, very big stopping of cars.
所以严重的交通堵塞就是非常非常大的车辆停滞。
Now our next word explains why sometimes there is a traffic jam.
现在我们的下一个词解释了为什么有时会有交通堵塞。
Well we found out that there was a huge pileup.
我们发现发生了一起严重的连环追尾事故。
A pileup.
连环追尾。
A huge pileup.
严重的连环追尾。
Okay, a huge pileup.
好的，严重的连环追尾。
Now if a pileup is another way of saying an accident, right?
现在连环追尾是事故的另一种说法，对吧？
Yeah, an accident with many cars and they all get piled on top of each other.
是的，涉及很多车的事故，它们都堆叠在一起。
All right, so many cars got into an accident.
好吧，所以很多车发生了事故。
Yep.
是的。
So this could be a reason of why there was a traffic jam.
所以这可能是堵车的原因之一。
And also a reason for why you were late.
也是你迟到的原因。
All right.
好的。
Now the other person, Scott, also called and he said that he's running late.
现在另一个人，斯科特，也打电话说他快迟到了。
He's running late.
他快迟到了。
I'm running late.
我快迟到了。
Now if I'm running late, am I actually running somewhere?
如果我说“我快迟到了”，我真的在跑步吗？
What am I doing?
我在做什么？
What's happening?
发生了什么？
You are going to be late and you know you're going to be late.
你快要迟到了，而且你知道自己会迟到。
Okay, I know I'm going to be late.
好吧，我知道我要迟到了。
So I'll call you and I'll say, hey, I'm running a little bit late.
所以我会打电话给你说，嘿，我有点晚了。
Yeah, actually this is the most common thing I say when I'm going to be late and I think
是啊，实际上这是我要迟到时最常说的一句话，我觉得
it's really important to know how to use this phrase.
学会用这个短语真的很重要。
So let's hear some more examples.
那我们再听一些例子吧。
Example one, Jane is running late.
例子一：简快迟到了。
She'll be here in 10 minutes.
她十分钟后到。
Example two, traffic is really bad.
例子二：交通真的很糟糕。
So I'm running late.
所以我快迟到了。
Example three, I'm running a bit late.
例子三：我有点晚了。
So please start without me.
所以请不用等我先开始。
All right, perfect.
好的，完美。
So running late, a very common way of explaining that you're going to be late and well, it
所以“快迟到了”是一个非常常见的表达方式，用来解释你要迟到了，而且
makes you sound very native.
它让你听起来很地道。
Yeah, it's a great phrase.
是啊，这是个很棒的短语。
Now our last phrase that we heard, the reason why Scott was running late was because his
现在我们听到的最后一个短语，斯科特迟到的原因是他上一个会议超时了。
last meeting ran over.
好的，“超时”。
Okay, to run over.
我的会议超时了。
My meeting ran over.
Now ran over, my meeting ran over, it means it went too far?
“超时”，我的会议超时了，意思是它拖得太久了？
Well, when something runs over, it goes longer.
嗯，当某件事“超时”时，意味着它持续的时间更长。
Okay, longer than expected.
好的，比预期的时间长。
Yeah, so a meeting can run over or an appointment can run over.
是啊，所以会议可以超时，或者预约也可以超时。
So I can say, my meeting ran over 15 minutes, I'm going to be a little bit late.
所以我可以这么说：我的会议超时了15分钟，我会晚一点到。
That's right, a great excuse.
没错，是个很好的借口。
Very good.
非常好。
Five great words and well, I think it's time for us to listen to this dialogue and understand
五个很棒的词，好吧，我觉得是时候听一下这段对话了，理解
these words as they were used in the dialogue and then we'll come back and take a look
这些词在对话中的用法，然后我们再回来看看。
at more phrases.
更多短语。
Where is everyone?
大家都去哪儿了？
We were supposed to start 15 minutes ago.
我们本应在15分钟前开始。
Joe called and said she'd be here in a sec.
乔打电话说她马上就到。
She said she got tied up with a client.
她说她被一个客户缠住了。
Sorry, I'm late everyone.
抱歉，我迟到了，各位。
There was a huge traffic jam on the highway this morning.
今天早上高速公路上堵车很严重。
Morning everyone.
大家早上好。
Were you stuck in traffic as well, Jess?
杰丝，你也堵在路上了吗？
There was a huge pileup on the highway and traffic was backed up for miles.
高速公路上发生了严重的连环追尾，堵了好几英里。
Scott just called and said that he's running late.
斯科特刚打电话说他迟到了。
His last meeting ran over, but he's on his way now.
他上一个会议超时了，但他现在正在路上。
Guys, this is not acceptable.
各位，这不可接受。
If I say the meeting starts at 10, the meeting starts at 10, not 10.01 and definitely not
如果我说会议10点开始，那就是10点开始，不是10点01分，更不是
10.20.
10点20分。
All right, let's get started.
好了，我们开始吧。
So the first thing I want to talk about is our-
所以第一件事我想谈谈我们的——
I'm really sorry everyone.
真的很抱歉，各位。
I know I'm late, but really it's not my fault.
我知道我迟到了，但这真的不是我的错。
I was getting a coffee at Starbucks and the line was way too long.
我在星巴克买咖啡，队伍太长了。
I was waiting for 20 minutes to get my coffee.
我等了20分钟才拿到咖啡。
Okay, we got some more great phrases for describing being late.
好了，我们又学到了一些描述迟到的好短语。
Let's look at them now in Fluency Builder.
现在让我们在流利度练习中看看它们。
Fluency Builder.
流利度练习。
When Jo called, she said she'd be there in a sec.
乔打电话时，她说她马上就到。
I'll be here in a sec.
我马上就到。
So when someone will be here in a sec, it means they'll be here very soon, right?
所以当有人说“马上就到”，意思就是他们很快就到，对吧？
Okay, I'll be here in a sec.
好的，我马上就到。
I'll be there in a sec.
我马上就到。
But what about this word sec?
但“sec”这个词呢？
It's a short way of saying second.
它是“second”的简写。
So sec.
所以是“sec”。
A sec.
“a sec”。
Now, it's an exaggeration obviously because you won't be there in one second, but you
这显然是一种夸张，因为你不会在一秒内到达，但你
just explaining that you'll be there very, very soon.
只是解释你很快就会到。
What about the difference between I'll be here in a sec and I'll be here in a minute?
“我马上就到”和“我一会儿就到”有什么区别？
Well, if you say I'll be there in a sec, it means like I'll be there in one minute, right?
嗯，如果你说“我马上就到”，意思是我一分钟内就到，对吧？
But if you say, oh, I'll be there in a minute, it could be a minute or more like three or
但如果你说“哦，我一会儿就到”，可能是一分钟，也可能更像三、
four or five minutes.
四或五分钟。
Yeah, I think that's true.
嗯，我觉得确实是这样。
Now, again, going back to this traffic issue, we saw that somebody was stuck in traffic.
现在，再回到这个交通问题，我们看到有人堵在路上了。
To be stuck in traffic.
堵在路上。
I got stuck in traffic.
我堵在路上了。
Now when you're stuck in traffic, you can't drive because there are too many cars stopped
当你堵在路上时，你没法开车，因为太多车停着
on the highway.
在高速公路上。
So you are actually in the traffic jam.
所以你实际上就在交通堵塞中。
Yeah, you're stopped there for like 20 minutes.
是啊，你在那儿停了大概20分钟。
You can't move.
你动不了。
Okay, I'm stuck in traffic.
好吧，我堵在路上了。
I'm going to be late.
我要迟到了。
Really great excuse.
真是个绝佳的借口。
And the reason they were stuck in traffic was because traffic was backed up for miles.
他们堵在路上的原因是，交通堵塞绵延数英里。
Okay, traffic is backed up for miles.
好吧，交通堵塞绵延数英里。
To be backed up for miles.
绵延数英里。
Now, if I say the traffic is backed up for miles, it means that it's very long or how
如果我说交通堵塞绵延数英里，意思是它很长，还是
does that work?
怎么理解？
Well, okay, imagine there is an accident and that has caused the traffic jam and the cars
嗯，想象一下，有一起事故导致了交通堵塞，车辆
are lined up for many miles behind you.
在你后面排了好几英里长。
Okay, so it's backed up.
所以就是堵住了。
From that point, there are many miles of cars waiting to pass.
从那个点开始，有数英里的车在等着通过。
Yep, so it's backed up for miles.
对，所以就是堵了好几英里。
Very good.
非常好。
So great phrases.
很棒的短语。
And I think it's appropriate for us to listen to the dialogue for the very last time and
我觉得现在适合再听一遍对话，最后一次，
then we'll come back and talk a little bit more about this being on time issue.
然后我们回来再聊聊这个准时的问题。
Where's everyone?
大家都去哪儿了？
We're supposed to start 15 minutes ago.
我们本该15分钟前就开始的。
Joe called and said she'd be here in a sec.
乔打电话说她马上就到。
She said she got tied up with a client.
她说她被一个客户缠住了。
Sorry, I'm late, everyone.
抱歉，我迟到了，各位。
There was a huge traffic jam on the highway this morning.
今天早上高速公路上大堵车。
Morning, everyone.
早上好，各位。
Are you stuck in traffic as well, Jess?
你也堵在路上了吗，杰丝？
There was a huge pileup on the highway and traffic was backed up for miles.
高速公路上发生了多车连环相撞，交通堵塞绵延数英里。
Scott just called and said that he's running late.
斯科特刚打电话说他快迟到了。
His last meeting ran over, but he's on his way now.
他上一个会议超时了，但他现在正在路上。
Guys, this is not acceptable.
各位，这不可接受。
If I say the meeting starts at 10, the meeting starts at 10, not 10.01 and definitely not
如果我说会议10点开始，那就是10点开始，不是10点01分，更不是
10.20.
10点20分。
All right, let's get started.
好了，我们开始吧。
So the first thing I want to talk about is our...
所以我想谈的第一件事是我们的……
I'm really sorry, everyone.
真的很抱歉，各位。
I know I'm late, but really it's not my fault.
我知道我迟到了，但这真的不是我的错。
I was getting a coffee at Starbucks and the line was way, way too long.
我在星巴克买咖啡，队伍排得太长了。
I was waiting for 20 minutes to get my coffee.
我等了二十分钟才拿到咖啡。
Well, Marco, I know that ideas about time and ideas about being late are different in
嗯，马可，我知道关于时间和迟到的观念在不同
different countries.
国家是不同的。
Yeah, in different countries, people treat time or being on time in different ways.
是的，在不同国家，人们对时间或守时的看法不同。
Yeah, like I'm from Canada and I look at being on time really different than you do, right?
是啊，比如我来自加拿大，我对守时的看法和你很不一样，对吧？
Yes, because for example, if you call for a meeting at nine o'clock, usually people
是的，因为举例来说，如果你通知九点开会，通常人们
will be there at nine o'clock because the meeting will start.
会在九点到，因为会议会准时开始。
In America.
在美国。
Right, in America.
对，在美国。
Now, for example, in Latin America, we do have this, what we call sometimes the Latino
现在，比如在拉丁美洲，我们确实有所谓的
time or Hispanic time, which is like nine o'clock is like the time that everyone should
拉丁时间或西班牙时间，就是九点大概是大家应该
be there.
到的时间。
But until people get there, get their coffee and whatever, then it'll be 9.15, maybe up
但等大家到了、拿了咖啡什么的，可能就九点十五分，甚至
to 9.30.
到九点半了。
And I think it's a little bit even more noticeable when we're talking about social events.
我觉得在社交活动上这一点更明显。
Like if you go to someone's house for dinner in Canada, if they say, come to my house at
比如在加拿大，如果你去别人家吃晚饭，他们说六点
six o'clock for dinner, you'll be there at 6.05, right?
来我家吃饭，你会在六点零五分到，对吧？
Okay, yeah.
嗯，是的。
Yeah, usually you'll be there only a couple of minutes after the time that was specified
是的，通常你只会比约定的时间晚几分钟到，
just to, you know, give the house owner a little bit of time.
你知道，给主人留点时间。
But if we have a dinner invitation for six, we know that it's not really going to begin
但如果我们收到六点的晚餐邀请，我们知道不会真的
eating at six, so people will get there at 6.30 or seven.
六点就开始吃，所以人们会在六点半或七点到。
And of course, food isn't ready until like maybe eight or nine.
当然，食物可能要到八点或九点才准备好。
But in German countries, from what I know, you've got to be there.
但在德语国家，据我所知，你必须准时到。
If they say be there at six, you're there at 6.00, right?
如果他们说到六点，你就得六点到，对吧？
Not 6.01.
不是六点零一分。
And also, I think it's about when people start work, right?
而且，我觉得这也和人们开始工作的时间有关，对吧？
How on time you have to begin work.
你上班必须多准时。
Sometimes it's acceptable to be 10 or 15 minutes so-called late, but in other places, you know.
有时候迟到十分钟或十五分钟是可以接受的，但在其他地方，你知道的。
Yeah, North America, if you're supposed to start work at nine, you have to be at your
是啊，在北美，如果你应该九点开始工作，你必须九点
desk working at nine.
坐在办公桌前开始工作。
At nine.
九点整。
Yeah.
是的。
Yeah, see that in other countries, people get there at nine, get their coffee, maybe
是啊，你看在其他国家，人们九点到，拿杯咖啡，可能
take a quick glance at their emails or the newspaper and then, you know, start working
快速扫一眼邮件或报纸，然后，你知道，大概
at around 9.30 or 10.
九点半或十点才开始工作。
So I guess the important thing is to know what the tradition is in the country where
所以我想重要的是要了解你所在国家的
you are.
传统。
Exactly.
没错。
So come to our website, EnglishPod.com and let us know how it works in your countries.
所以请访问我们的网站 EnglishPod.com，告诉我们你们国家的情况。
I know that many different countries have a different way of treating time, so share
我知道很多国家对待时间的方式不同，所以请
it with us.
和我们分享。
Yes, and remember, if you have any questions, please ask them at the website as well.
是的，记住，如果你有任何问题，也请在网站上提问。
We're out of time today, but until next time, thanks for listening and goodbye.
今天时间到了，但下次再见，感谢收听，再见。
Bye-bye.
拜拜。